haskell a statically typed general-purpose language made famous for
haskell 一种静态类型的通用语言，以
expanding the minds of developers into the functional programming paradigm you
将开发人员的思想扩展到函数式编程范式而闻名，你
see haskell is a purely functional language based on lambda calculus which
看到 haskell 是一种基于 lambda 演算的纯函数式语言，这
means a function always produces the same output given the same input unlike
意味着一个函数在相同的输入下总是产生相同的输出，这
an imperative language your code can't modify the inputs or produce side
与命令式语言不同 你的代码不能修改输入或产生
effects that would otherwise change the behavior of the application it was first
副作用，否则会改变应用程序的行为它最初
developed in 1987 and named after logician haskell curry whose work had a
是在 1987 年开发的，以逻辑学家 haskell curry 的名字命名，他的工作
massive influence on the functional programming world it's been used to
对函数式编程世界产生了巨大的影响，它被用来
build a wide variety of server-side applications like the hasura api
构建一个 各种各样的服务器端应用程序，例如 facebook 上的 hasura api
platform spam filtering at facebook and compilers for other languages like elm
平台垃圾邮件过滤和其他语言（例如 elm
and purescript and it's responsible for a countless number of blog posts about
和 purescript）的编译器，它负责无数关于
monads in haskell you write declarative code where the program is a single
haskell 中 monad 的博客文章 你编写声明性代码，程序是单个
expression that is executed by evaluating that expression it also uses
表达式 通过评估该表达式执行它也使用
lazy evaluation which means an expression is not evaluated until it's
la  zy 评估，这意味着表达式在被函数实际使用之前不会被评估，
actually used by a function this can result in big performance gains but
这可能会带来巨大的性能提升，但
unpredictable memory use at runtime all data in a haskell program is immutable
在运行时内存使用不可预测Haskell 程序中的所有数据都是不可变的
which produces a lot of memory garbage so it contains a garbage collector to
，这会产生大量内存垃圾，因此它包含垃圾收集器
clean things up to get started install the glasgow haskell compiler then create
清理一切以开始安装 glasgow haskell 编译器然后创建
a file ending in dot hs we don't work with statements here only expressions
一个以点 hs 结尾的文件我们不使用这里的语句只有表达式
which is code that will always evaluate to a value create a string with double
，它是总是评估为一个值的代码创建一个带双引号的字符串
quotes then give it a name with the equal sign the value is immutable and
然后给它一个 带等号的名称 该值是不可变的，
can never be changed the type will automatically be inferred or we can
永远不能更改 类型将自动推断，或者我们现在可以
strongly type it with a double colon as a list of characters now to define a
用双冒号作为字符列表强输入它来定义一个
function start with a name followed by the arguments that you want to pass to
函数，该函数以名称开头，后跟您的参数 想在右边传递给
it on the right side define the logic of the function and it will automatically
它定义函数的逻辑，它会
return a value based on the result of the expression we can also statically
根据表达式的结果自动返回一个值，我们也可以 o
type it using an arrow to separate the argument and return value we can call
使用箭头静态键入它来分隔参数和返回值我们可以
the function by referencing its name with the arguments all values including
通过使用参数引用它的名称来调用函数所有值包括
functions are first class which means they can be passed as arguments to other
函数都是第一类这意味着
functions if we try to print the result to the standard output we get an error
如果我们尝试打印它们可以作为参数传递给其他函数 结果到标准输出我们得到一个错误
that's because working with io creates a side effect to write a program that
，这是因为使用 io 会产生一个副作用来编写一个
actually does something we write a main function with a do block here we can
实际执行某些操作的程序我们在这里编写一个带有 do 块的主函数我们可以
chain together a sequence of actions where the side effects are abstracted
将一系列动作链接在一起，其中副作用被抽象出来
away made possible by a mathematical concept known as the monad which is
被称为 monad 的数学概念
basically a wrapper that can make functional code more modular now to run
使之成为可能
your code you can use the interactive interpreter or compile it to an
executable by running ghc make this has been haskell in 100 seconds hit the like
秒点击喜欢
button and subscribe if you want to see more short videos like this thanks for
按钮并订阅如果您想看到更多这样的短视频感谢
watching and i will see you in the next one
观看，我会在下一个看到你